Your Majesty,
صاحب الجلالة
this is the divorce agreement between Young Lady Xie and me.
هذه وثيقة طلاقي من ابنة عائلة شيه
The bond between her and me ends here.
لقد انتهت علاقتي بها
This is for your review.
أرفعها إلى جلالتك للاطلاع عليها
Your Majesty.
صاحب الجلالة
Regarding the Beifu Reform,
بخصوص إصلاح الحامية الشمالية
what do you intend to do?
ما هي خطتك؟
Your Majesty,
ردًا على جلالتك
my reform will proceed in three steps.
تقوم خطتي على ثلاث مراحل
Firstly, eliminate long-standing flaws,
أولًا، القضاء على مكامن الفساد
restructure the military system,
وإصلاح النظام العسكري
appoint talents of humble origins,
واستقطاب الكفاءات من عامة الناس
and employ generals by ability alone.
وتولية الأكفاء دون تمييز
Secondly, forge stronger armor and weapons,
ثانيًا، تطوير الدروع والسلاح
and expand the transportation of provisions
وتوسيع قنوات نقل الحبوب وخطوط الإمداد
to ensure steady military supplies.
لضمان عدم نقص المؤن العسكرية أبدًا
Thirdly...
...أما ثالثًا
What is Prince Qi's take on this plan?
وما رأي أمير تشي في هذه الخطة؟
Prince Qi and I share a bond like brothers
أنا وأمير تشي مقربان كالإخوة
as well as deep trust.
وتجمعنا رابطة ثقة مطلقة
I believe that
وأثق أنه
as long as His Highness and I join hands...
...طالما عملتُ أنا وسموه بتناغم
Even today,
حتى الآن
you still think
هل ما زلت تظن
that you and Prince Qi share a bond like brothers
أن أمير تشي بمثابة أخ لك
as well as deep trust?
وأن بينكما رابطة ثقة مطلقة؟
Now,
والآن
do you understand
هل أدركت
why I insisted on keeping Xie Jiayu
لماذا أصررت على إبقاء شيه جيا يوي
by your side?
إلى جانبك؟
I understand now.
لقد أدركت اليوم
The way of checks and balances
إن فن الحفاظ على التوازن
is the emperor's art.
هو جوهر الحكم الإمبراطوري
Therefore,
ولهذا
Xie Jiayu
شيه جيا يوي
is my way
هي وسيلتي
of keeping a balance between you and Prince Qi.
لتحقيق التوازن بينك وبين أمير تشي
[Key to the Phoenix Heart]
[مفتاح قلب العنقاء]
[Episode 15]
[الحلقة الخامسة عشرة]
[Lingfeng Fort]
[حصن لينغفنغ]
[Cui Jun, Master of the Cui family]
[تسوي جيون، سيد عائلة تسوي]
Father, why are you so fond of pine trees?
لِمَ تعشق الصنوبر والسرو إلى هذا الحد يا أبي؟
They can endure cold and drought.
لأنهما يصمدان أمام البرد والجفاف
Scatter a handful of seeds anywhere,
تكفي أن تُنثر حفنة من البذور عشوائيًا
and they will grow.
لتزدهر وتنمو أينما حطت
But Mother told me that
لكن أمي أخبرتني
you loved loquat flowers the most when you were young.
أنك في شبابك كنت تحب زهور الأسكدنيا كثيرًا
Even Mother loved making loquat wine the most.
وكانت هي أيضًا تحب تخمير مشروب الإسكدنيا
People change.
الناس يتغيرون
I will set off for Jiankang in a few days.
سأغادر إلى جيانكانغ قريبًا
I'm afraid that, by this time
وفي مثل هذا الوقت من العام القادم
next year, I won't be able to accompany you
أخشى ألا أتمكن من مرافقتك
to pay respects to Mother together.
لزيارة قبر أمي
Today,
لذا اليوم
let me pour wine for you
اسمح لي يا أبي
one last time, Father.
أن أصب لك الكأس الأخيرة
You have arranged such a grand marriage
لقد رتبت لي يا أبي
for me, Father,
زواجًا يعده الناس أعظم زيجة
but I only feel restless and uneasy.
ومع ذلك، لا أشعر إلا بالوجل
The Cui family is hailed as the top noble family.
تُعرف عائلة تسوي بأنها أعظم العائلات الأرستقراطية
But what have you done, Father?
لكن هل تظن يا أبي
Do you really think no one knows?
أن الناس جميعًا يجهلون ما اقترفته؟
You've privately run illegal mines
فأنت استخرجت المعادن خفية
and tricked women
واستدرجت النساء
into dying in the mines unjustly.
ليلقين حتفهن ظلمًا داخل المنجم
Your actions are
ما اقترفته يا أبي
enough to ruin our Cui family completely.
كفيل بإهلاك عائلة تسوي جميعًا
Shao'an!
شاو آن
You don't need to call him.
لا داعي لمناداته يا ابي
I have already led Shao'an out of Lingfeng Fort.
لقد نقلت شاو آن بالفعل بعيدًا عن حصن لينغفنغ
And I also told Xie Jiayu the hiding place
وأخبرت شيه جيا يوي بمكان اختباء
of her mother, Princess Yunzhao.
والدتها الأميرة يونتشاو
By now, they must have left Lingfeng Fort.
ولا بد أنهما قد غادرتا حصن لينغفنغ الآن
Everything about Lingfeng Fort is about to be exposed.
وجميع أسرار حصن لينغفنغ على وشك أن تُكشف
Guards!
!أيها الحراس
If you plead guilty together with me today,
إن مثُلنا اليوم للعدالة معًا اليوم
our Cui family might still have a chance to survive.
فسيبقى لعائلة تسوي بصيص أمل
Lady Jiayu, my young lady ordered that
يا آنسة، لقد أوصت سيدتي
after we get Her Highness out,
أنه بمجرد إنقاذ الأميرة
you must leave Lingfeng Fort immediately.
عليكِ مغادرة حصن لينغفنغ فورًا
Do you really think I'm stupid?
هل تظنينني أحمق؟
I knew Lingyi was a traitor
كنت أعلم منذ البداية أن أختي تخون العائلة
and wanted to help you save the Princess.
وأنها تتآمر لمساعدتكِ في إنقاذ الأميرة
Where is Xiao Wuyi?
وأين شياو وو يي؟
Behind you.
خلفك مباشرة
Xiao Wuyi, how did you know there was a trap?
شياو وو يي، كيف عرفت أن الأمر مكيدة؟
Were we also tricked by Young Lady Cui?
هل خدعتنا الآنسة تسوي لينغ يي أيضًا؟
Cui Lingyi didn't trick us.
تسوي لينغ يي لم تخدعنا
Instead, she was also deceived by them.
بل هم من خدعوها
Last night, Cui Lingyi spread the fake news
الليلة الماضية، سرّبت تسوي لينغ يي خبرًا كاذبًا
that we had fled from Lingfeng Fort.
بأننا هربنا من حصن لينغفنغ
And you
ثم خرجتَ أنت
searched for us with great fanfare in the middle of the night.
تطاردنا علنًا في جوف الليل
Wasn't it to deliberately tell us that
ألم ترد بذلك أن تقنعنا
you had left the city?
أنك غادرت المدينة؟
If my guess is right,
ولو صحّ ظني
you lurked in the dark
فما إن غادرتَ المدينة
soon after you left the city.
حتى عدت خفية واختبأت
We encountered no obstacles at all
واليوم في طريقنا إلى الجبل الخلفي
on our way to the back mountain.
لم يعترضنا أحد
Including that maid who suddenly appeared just now,
وحتى تلك الخادمة التي ظهرت فجأة
everything is suspicious.
كل ذلك لم يكن طبيعيًا
Someone must have lured us here intentionally.
لا بد أن شخصًا ما استدرجنا إلى هنا عمدًا
You think you can bring me down this way?
هل تظنين أن هذا كافٍ لإسقاطي؟
You think
هل تظنين
you can save our Cui family just like this?
أنكِ بهذه الطريقة يمكنكِ إنقاذ عائلة تسوي؟
You think I would drink the poisoned wine?
هل ظننتِ أنني سأشرب المشروب المسموم؟
I am the Master of Lingfeng Fort.
أنا سيد حصن لينغفنغ
And you will soon enter the Eastern Palace and marry
وأنتِ ستدخلين القصر الشرقي قريبًا
Prince Qi to become his consort.
لتصبحي زوجة أمير تشي
In the future, you will be the first lady
وستسيرين مستقبلًا على خطى إمبراطورة ونشي
like Empress Wenxi.
وتغدين أمًّا للأمة
Our Cui family has laid low for over 20 years
لقد ظلت عائلة تسوي تنتظر الفرصة لأكثر من عشرين عامًا
just for today
ألم يكن كل ذلك من أجل هذا اليوم بالذات
to revive our family.
الذي يمكننا فيه استعادة مجد عائلتنا؟
But you insisted on ruining the glory of our Cui family
لكنكِ تصرّين في هذه اللحظة
at this very moment
على تحطيم مجد عائلة تسوي
and destroying my 20 years of great efforts.
وهدم ما بنيته طوال عشرين عامًا
I suppose your sister
أظن أن أختك الكبرى
has already been captured by now.
قد وقعت في الأسر الآن
Hand over the Princess,
سلّم الأميرة
or I'll kill you right now.
وإلا قتلتك حالًا
Ouch! It hurts...
!مؤلم، مؤلم، مؤلم
Mother!
!أمي
What an impressive scheme.
!يا لها من خطة مُحكمة
Young Lord Xiao,
ولي العهد شياو
I've heard a lot about you.
لقد سمعت الكثير عنك
Put the sword down.
ألقِ سيفك
Father.
!أبي
Father,
أبي
Lingyi is already engaged
لقد خُطبت أختي الكبرى
and will get married soon.
ولم يبقَ على زفافها إلا القليل
Xiao Wuyi and the Princess
والآن شياو وو يي والأميرة
are both in our hands now.
في قبضتنا
There won't be any problem.
ولم يصبهما أذى
Please let Lingyi go, Father.
أرجوك يا أبي، اعفُ عن أختي
Father,
أبي
are you still going to use me
هل ما زلت تريد استغلالي
to force Shao'an to do evil?
لإجبار شاو آن على ارتكاب الشر؟
Lingyi...
أختي الكبرى
Are you still going to use Shao'an to force me
ما زلت تريد استخدام شاو آن للضغط عليّ
to cover up the truth for the family?
كي تستر حقيقة ما اقترفه أفراد العائلة؟
Since we were young,
منذ صغرنا
you've kept instigating conflicts between Shao'an and me.
كنت دائمًا تزرع العداوة بيني وبين شاو آن
Whenever you praised me,
وكلما مدحتني
you'd scold Shao'an
كنتَ توبخ شاو آن
as if he was worthless.
وتصفه بأنه عديم الفائدة تمامًا
I didn't understand back then.
لم أكن أدرك ذلك حينها
I was only at odds with Shao'an
وكنتُ أتشاجر مع أخي الأصغر
in order to please you.
فقط لأحظى برضاك
What you want is never children,
لكنك لم تعتبرنا يومًا أبناءك
but merely
بل مجرد
two pawns under your control!
قطعتي شطرنج تتحكم بهما كما تشاء
I'd rather die than be manipulated by you again!
أفضل الموت على أن أسمح لك بالتلاعب بي مجددًا
Do you think Princess Yunzhao
هل تظنين أن الأميرة يونتشاو
is some sort of good person?
امرأة طيبة؟
Do you think she stayed
هل تظنين أنها بقيت
in order to expose the Cui family?
لكشف أسرار عائلة تسوي؟
Do you think she lured Xiao Wuyi
هل تظنين أنها أحضرت شياو وو يي
over here to help you reveal
لمساعدتكِ في كشف
the dark side of the Cui family?
قبائح عائلة تسوي؟
Everything she did was for the Phoenix Heart Token I hold!
لقد جاءت من أجل أمر تشيوه قو
Whatever her purpose,
لا يعنيني سبب مجيئها
all I want is for her to destroy
طالما أنها تدمر
everything here!
كل شيء هنا، فهذا يكفيني
Lingyi,
!أختي الكبرى
how could you talk to Father like that?
كيف تجرئين على التحدث مع أبي هكذا؟
Kneel and apologize to him!
اركعي واعتذري لأبي
Shao'an,
شاو آن
the real lunatic in our family
المجنون الحقيقي في عائلتنا
is our father!
هو والدنا العزيز
Lingyi...
!أختي الكبرى
Princess Yunzhao,
الأميرة يونتشاو
your daughter and your reinforcement
ابنتكِ وقوات النجدة
are both in my hands.
جميعهم في قبضتي
Do you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token?
أما آن لكِ أن تسلّمي أمر تشيوه قو؟
Mother.
أمي
Are you alright?
كيف حالكِ؟
Cui Jun, how dare you
!تسوي جيون، ما أجرأك
tamper with my letter?
كيف تجرؤ على تحريف رسالتي؟
I did use the family letter to inform Xiao Wuyi,
لقد أرسلت رسالة عائلية لإبلاغ شياو وو يي
but I did something with the letter.
لكنني أخفيت فيها إشارة
It should never have reached Jiayu.
بحيث لا تصل إلى جيا يوي أبدًا
You deliberately set it up
إذًا أنت من دبّر الأمر عمدًا
to lure Jiayu over here.
لاستدراج جيا يوي إلى هنا
Yes, I did it.
نعم، أنا
I also needed to know
أريد أن أعرف أيضًا
who you plotted to get the Phoenix Heart Token
من أجل من تسعين أيتها الأميرة يونتشاو للحصول على أمر تشيوه قو
and the mines for, right?
والمنجم؟
Mother,
أمي
what does he mean?
ما معنى هذا؟
Your Highness, you're indeed a good mother.
الأميرة حقًا أم عظيمة
Everything you did was for your daughter.
كل ما فعلتِه كان من أجل ابنتكِ
System reform, northern expedition—
إصلاح النظام، والحملة الشمالية
actually, the one who really needs the minerals
ومن يحتاج إلى هذه الثروات المعدنية حقًا
is Young Lord Xiao.
هو ولي العهد شياو
But your daughter is in his hands.
لكن بما أن ابنتكِ في قبضتهم
As her mother, of course you have to yield.
فكيف لأمٍ ألا تخضع لمطالبهم؟
Therefore, you came to Guazhou for Young Lord Xiao
إذًا، جئتِ إلى قواتشو من أجل ولي العهد شياو
to find the Phoenix Heart Token.
بحثًا عن أمر تشيوه قو
So you really have
إذًا أمر تشيوه قو
the Phoenix Heart Token.
بحوزتك بالفعل
You found this mine
وهذا المنجم
under the guidance of the Phoenix Heart Token.
عثرت عليه باتباع إرشادات أمر تشيوه قو
I have indeed decoded it.
لقد فككت شفرته بالفعل
So there's no way I can let you go.
ولهذا تحديدًا لا يمكنني أن أدعكم ترحلون
Cui Jun,
تسوي جيون
even if you kill and silence us all, the secret
حتى لو قتلتمونا جميعًا لإسكاتنا
of the Cuis and the Phoenix Heart Token still can't remain hidden.
فلن تستطيعوا إخفاء حقيقة عائلة تسوي ولا سر أمر تشيوه قو
Young Lord Xiao,
ولي العهد شياو
instead of worrying about me,
بدلًا من القلق عليّ
right now,
يجدر بك
you'd better worry about yourself.
أن تقلق على نفسك الآن
The secret guards you planted have been exposed.
لقد كُشف أمر حراسك السريين الذين زرعتهم
No one will come to save you anymore.
ولن يأتي أحد لإنقاذك
Princess, I'll only give you 2 days.
أيتها الأميرة، أمنحكِ يومين فقط
If you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
إذا استمريتِ في رفض تسليم أمر تشيوه قو
your daughter will die for sure.
فإن ابنتكِ هالكة لا محالة
[Court of Judicial Review]
[محكمة دالي]
Look what I got for you.
انظر ماذا أحضرت لك
I didn't expect that, after so many years,
لم أتوقع أنه بعد كل هذه الأعوام
[Yang Zhang, Guazhou County Sheriff]
[يانغ تشانغ، مفتش مقاطعة قواتشو]
you still remember that I
ما زلت تتذكر يا معلمي
love the longans from Nanzhou the most, Master.
أنني أعشق فاكهة اللونجان من نانتشو
This time,
هذه المرة
you did a great job.
لقد أحسنتَ صنعًا
You sent Cui Jun's contaminated military provisions
أوصلت مؤن تسوي جيون الفاسدة
to the Northern Border,
إلى الحدود الشمالية
leading to an outbreak of plague in the Beifu Army.
فتفشّى وباء مفاجئ في صفوف جيش الشمال
It also caused the noble families
وبذلك انتقدت العائلات الأرستقراطية
to impeach the Beifu Reform one after another
إصلاح الحامية الشمالية بشدة
and quietly
ثم، ودون أن يدرك أحد ذلك
lured Xiao Wuyi to Cui Jun's place.
استدرجت شياو وو يي إلى مكان تسوي جيون
It's been over 2 decades.
لقد مضى أكثر من عشرين عامًا
This grudge should finally come to an end.
وحان وقت إنهاء هذا الثأر
Master,
معلمي
I heard that the unjust case of the An and Lu families back then
سمعتُ أن المظلمة التي حاقت بعشيرتي آن ولو آنذاك
was all traced back to Empress Wenxi of the Cui family.
كانت بسبب إمبراطورة ونشي من عائلة تسوي
Is it true?
فهل هذا صحيح؟
If Xiao Wuyi can bring down
إذا تمكن شياو وو يي هذه المرة
the Cuis, Empress Wenxi's maternal family,
من الإطاحة بعائلة إمبراطورة ونشي
this time,
وهي عائلة تسوي
the secret of the An and Lu families from back then
فلعل أسرار عشيرتي آن ولو القديمة
might finally come to light.
تُكشف أخيرًا للعالم
If so,
وإن تحقق ذلك
you will be
فستكون أنت
my greatest benefactor
أعظم محسن لي، أنا شيه هواي قوي
for the rest of my life.
في حياتي كلها
Your grace of teaching gave me a second life,
فضلك عليّ كمن وهبني حياةً جديدة
equal to my parents' care and love.
ويضاهي فضل الوالدين في التربية والرعاية
Now that I got a chance to do you a favor,
ولو أفنيت عمري في خدمتك
even if I die for it,
وضحيت بروحي وفاءً لك
I still can't repay you enough.
لما وفيت بعض جميلك
It is already the greatest fortune of my life!
وذلك أعظم شرفٍ نلته في حياتي
[Imperial Academy]
[الأكاديمية الإمبراطورية]
Master, we just got the news from the Court of Judicial Review.
سيدي، وردت للتو أنباء من محكمة دالي
[Bingzhu, butler of Xie Mansion]
[بينغ تشو، كبير الخدم في قصر شيه]
Yang Zhang, Guazhou County Sheriff,
تفيد بأن يانغ تشانغ، مفتش مقاطعة قواتشو
committed suicide in prison out of fear.
قد انتحر في السجن خشية العقاب
The body can't be kept.
لا يجوز أن تبقى جثته
Send his body to Puzhao Temple tonight and burn it.
انقلها الليلة إلى معبد بوتشاو لحرقها
Understood.
أمرك
Anything else?
هل هناك أمر آخر؟
The subordinates Young Lord Xiao planted outside Lingfeng Fort
لقد أُبيد جميع رجال ولي العهد شياو
have all been wiped out.
المرابطين حول حصن لينغفنغ
Cui Jun has captured Young Lord Xiao.
وسيطر تسوي جيون على ولي العهد شياو
How could Xiao Wuyi have made
كيف كانت استعدادات شياو وو يي
such hasty preparations?
بهذا القدر من السذاجة والإهمال؟
Our informant reported
تفيد التقارير
that Young Lord Xiao entered
بأن ولي العهد شياو دخل حصن لينغفنغ مبكرًا
Lingfeng Fort early for our young lady.
من أجل الآنسة الشابة
Xie Jiayu?
شيه جيا يوي؟
How come she's in Guazhou?
كيف انتهى بها المطاف في قواتشو؟
Not only the Young Lady,
ليست الآنسة وحدها
but the Princess is also there.
بل الأميرة أيضًا هناك
Her Highness wrote to the Young Lady and made her go to Guazhou.
والأميرة هي من استدعت الآنسة إلى قواتشو
Cui Jun has seized them all now,
وهما الآن في قبضة تسوي جيون
using the Young Lady to force Her Highness to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token.
إنه يهدد الأميرة بالآنسة ليجبرها على تسليم أمر تشيوه قو
The Phoenix Heart Token?
أمر تشيوه قو؟
I see. Cui Jun is Empress Wenxi's older brother.
صحيح، تسوي جيون هو شقيق إمبراطورة ونشي
If Yunzhao has the Phoenix Heart Token
ولو كانت الأميرة يونتشاو تحمل أمر تشيوه قو
and wants to unite her old subordinates against Prince Qi,
وتسعى لتوحيد الحلفاء القدامى ضد أمير تشي
Cui Jun is the best ally.
فلن تجد خيرًا من تسوي جيون عونًا لها
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
was Cui Jun telling the truth
هل كان ما قاله تسوي جيون
just now?
صحيحًا؟
Did my mother look for
هل سعت أمي للحصول على أمر تشيوه قو
the Phoenix Heart Tokens for you?
من أجلك؟
Yes.
نعم
You could say that.
يمكنكِ قول ذلك
My mother never meddles in court politics.
لم تتدخل أمي قط في سياسات البلاط
If someone hadn't forced her,
ولولا أنها أُجبرت على ذلك
she wouldn't have taken the initiative to get involved.
لما دخلت ذلك الصراع بمحض إرادتها أبدًا
Did you use me to threaten her?
هل استخدمتني لتهديدها؟
No,
لا
I've never used you to threaten her.
لم أهددها بكِ قط
But this matter is complicated.
لكن الأمر مقعد أكثر مما تظنين
I'll explain it to you later.
سأشرحه لكِ لاحقًا
But my mother agreed to help you
لكن أمي وافقت على طلبك
because of me.
فقط من أجلي
I once thought that after my mother and father divorced,
ظننتُ أنه بعد انفصال أمي وأبي
she would finally be able to live for herself,
ستتمكن أمي أخيرًا من عيش حياتها الخاصة
travel to places she had never seen,
وترى الجبال والبحار التي لم ترها يومًا
and lead a carefree life she had never had.
وتعيش بحرية حُرمت منها طوال عمرها
I didn't expect that
ولم أتخيل أبدًا
she'd still be dragged into this because of me,
أنها ستتورط بسببي
utilized by others,
وأنها ستُستغل
and end up in such a desperate state.
وتُدفع إلى هذا المأزق
I once thought that
وظننت أيضًا
you cared about me in Prince Jing'an's Mansion
أن الرعاية التي أوليتني إياها في قصر أمير جينغآن
and allowed me to come and go freely,
والحرية التي منحتني إياها في الذهاب والإياب كما أشاء
all because you were just a good person.
كانت لأنك رجل صالح
I was too stupid.
لكنني كنت ساذجة جدًا
Everything I did
كل ما فعلته
was never about
لم يكن يومًا
making a deal with the Princess.
بهدف عقد صفقة مع الأميرة
Xie Jiayu,
شيه جيا يوي
did you really not
أما شعرتِ بذلك
feel anything at all?
ولو قليلًا؟
Am I wrong, Xiao Wuyi?
أليس الأمر كذلك يا شياو وو يي؟
You've been using me from the very beginning.
لقد كنت تستغلني طوال الوقت
At first, when you didn't even know who I was,
حين لم تكن تعرف هويتي في البداية
you used me to quell Prince Changsha's rebellion.
استغلتني لإخماد تمرد أمير تشانغشا
When you knew who I was,
وبمجرد أن اكتشفتَ هويتي الحقيقية
you used my freedom
استغللت حريتي
and my life
واستغللت حياتي
to force my mother to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
لإجبار أمي على تسليم أمر تشيوه قو
putting her in danger!
مُعرضًا إياها بذلك لخطر جسيم
Yes.
نعم
It's all my fault.
الخطأ يقع عليّ بالكامل
What is this sound?
ما هذا الصوت؟
Not the sound of a human.
ليس صوت إنسان
There is an underground river beneath this mine,
يوجد نهر جوفي تحت هذا المنجم
where the water is not clean.
ومياهه ملوثة
Taken or applied,
ومن يشرب منها أو يستخدمها
it drives people mad
يُصاب بحالة من الهياج الجنوني
and turns them into beasts,
ويتحول لوحش
just like him.
مثله تمامًا
Do you know how many people my father had killed
هل تدريان كم روحًا أزهق أبي
until he got such a monster?
ليربي وحشًا كهذا؟
No more struggling.
كف عن المقاومة
This candle is specially made.
هذا اللهب مُعد خصيصًا
You can't use your martial arts anymore.
لذا لا يمكنك استخدام فنونك القتالية
Hand over the Phoenix Heart Token.
سلم أمر تشيوه قو
Otherwise,
وإلا
I don't mind letting this monster
لن أمانع في ترك هذا الوحش
deal with Xie Jiayu.
يواجه شيه جيا يوي
Very well.
حسنًا
Release him.
أطلقوا سراحه
Jiayu!
جيا يوي
Xiao Wuyi!
شياو وو يي
-Stay here and watch. -Xiao Wuyi!
راقبوه من هنا - شياو وو يي -
He has little inner energy now.
لقد فقد معظم قوته الداخلية
How about we give him 15 minutes?
ما رأيكِ في منحه وقتًا يعادل احتراق نصف عود بخور؟
It won't take him 15 minutes.
إنه لا يحتاج إلى وقت احتراق نصف عود بخور
You trust him that much?
هل تثقين به إلى هذا الحد؟
He will win for sure.
سينتصر حتمًا
Xiao Wuyi...
شياو وو يي
Grand Tutor, you must've come
أن يأتي المعلم الأكبر في جنح الليل
late at night for something important.
يعني أن الأمر جلل
What on earth happened?
ما الذي حدث بالضبط؟
Have you heard of the Phoenix Heart Tokens?
هل سمعتِ عن أمر تشيوه قو؟
When the Phoenix Heart Tokens appear, peace shall be restored in the world.
عندما يظهر أمر تشيوه قو، يستقر العالم
Who in Ye hasn't heard about it?
من في يه الكبرى لم يسمع بهذه المقولة؟
It is the hope of the people.
إنه الأمل في قلوب الناس
What if Empress Wenxi really had the Phoenix Heart Tokens
إذا كانت إمبراطورة ونشي تمتلك حقًا أمر تشيوه قو
and passed them down?
وكان لا يزال متداولًا في هذا العالم
Since Yunzhao was her closest friend,
فإن الأميرة يونتشاو، بصفتها أقرب صديقاتها
and Cui Jun was her older brother,
وتسوي جيون، بصفته شقيقها
the two of them are the most likely
فهما الأجدر بأن يكونا
to be entrusted by Empress Wenxi.
ممن ائتمنتهما إمبراطورة ونشي وأودعت لديهما تلك الأمانة
Even if the Phoenix Heart Tokens truly exist,
حتى لو كان أمر تشيوه قو موجودًا حقًا
the Northern Qin people back then
فإن شعب تشين الشمالية آنذاك
already wiped out Crown Prince Wenxi.
أباد ولي عهد ونشي تمامًا منذ زمن
Those people only have the Phoenix Heart Tokens
وقد تكون تلك المجموعة محتفظة بأمر تشيوه قو
but not Crown Prince Wenxi.
ولكن في غياب ولي عهد ونشي
They pose no threat to my brother at all.
فإنهم لا يشكلون أي تهديد على أخي إطلاقًا
Your Highness,
أيتها الأميرة
what if I told you
ماذا لو أخبرتكِ
your brother
أن أخاكِ
is not of the Ye bloodline at all?
ليس من سلالة يه الكبرى على الإطلاق؟
Watch your words, Grand Tutor.
أيها المعلم الأكبر، انتبه لكلامك
Yunzhao has long suspected Prince Qi's origins.
لقد راود يونتشاو الشك في نسب أمير تشي منذ زمن
She went to Guazhou this time
ورحلتها إلى قواتشو هذه المرة
probably just to use
من المرجح أنها محاولة لاستخدام
the Phoenix Heart Token in her hands
أمر تشيوه قو الذي بحوزتها
to command the other Token holders
لإصدار الأوامر إلى سائر حَمَلة الأمر
and support the Imperial Li family of Ye again.
وإعادة دعم أفراد البيت الإمبراطوري المنحدرين من لي يه
How is that possible?
كيف يُعقل هذا؟
How could my brother not be...
...كيف يمكن لأخي ألا يكون
Your trip to Guazhou this time
ستذهبين إلى قواتشو هذه المرة
is nominally to escort the bride,
بحجة استقبال العروس
but the real purpose is to cooperate
لكن مهمتكِ الحقيقية
with Young Lord Xiao to capture the Cuis.
هي معاونة ولي العهد شياو في القبض على عائلة تسوي
Remember, besides purging the Cuis,
وتذكري، إلى جانب القضاء على عائلة تسوي
you absolutely cannot let the Phoenix Heart Token
إياكِ أن تدعي أمر تشيوه قو
fall into Xiao Wuyi's hands.
يقع في يد شياو وو يي
You must not
وبالتأكيد
let Yunzhao ruin Prince Qi's future.
لا تدعي يونتشاو تدمر مستقبل أمير تشي
Brother, the clothes are fixed.
أخي، لقد انتهيت من خياطة ثوبك
Try them on when you're free.
جرّبه عندما يتسع لك الوقت
Lejun.
له جيون
Put this on.
ضعي هذا معكِ
This sachet
كيس العطر هذا
was sewn for you
هو الذي خاطته لك والدتنا
by Mother back then.
بيديها قبل سنوات
I heard that a strange disease is raging in Guazhou.
سمعتُ أن وباءً غريبًا يجتاح قواتشو
It has Bishou lotuses inside,
يوجد بداخله زهرة اللوتس الخضراء
with detoxifying effects.
ولها أثر في طرد السموم
Since this was made by Mother,
وما دام من صنع والدتنا
it can definitely keep you safe on your journey.
فأنا على يقين أنه سيحميك طوال الطريق
Brother, you are so silly.
أنت حقًا ساذج يا أخي
It's been so many years.
لقد مضت أعوام عديدة
The effects must've long worn off.
وزال مفعول الدواء منذ زمن طويل
You will always be my brother.
لكنك تظل أخي
The brother I know
الأخ الذي أعرفه
is Li Mao, who has always
لي ماو الذي يعتمد علي
stuck with me through everything.
وأعتمد عليه
What?
ماذا؟
Don't worry, Brother.
اطمئن يا أخي
I will not fail your trust on this journey.
لن أخيب ثقتك بي
I will bring the Cui family to justice
سألقي القبض على عائلة تسوي
and return safe and sound.
وأعود إليك سالمة
You irritated me
أنت للتو
on purpose just now
استفززتني عمدًا
because you wanted me to help you kill him, right?
أردت أن أقتله نيابةً عنك، أليس كذلك؟
I've been sick of that bastard for a long time.
لطالما كرهت ذلك الوحش
You hated what your father has done,
أنت ساخط على تصرفات والدك
but you didn't dare to resist.
لكنك لا تجرؤ على مواجهته
So you could only use Xiao Wuyi and me as pawns.
لذا اتخذت مني ومن شياو وو يي وسيلة لتحقيق غايتك
My father would do anything
والدي مستعد لفعل أي شيء
for the Phoenix Heart Tokens.
للحصول على أمر تشيوه قو
I needed to see
وكان لا بد أن أرى
your determination and capabilities
مدى عزمكما وقدرتكما
to go against my father.
على مجابهته ومواجهته
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
when will your men arrive?
متى سيصل رجالك؟
It's fine if you don't want to tell me,
لا بأس إن لم ترغب في الإفصاح عن ذلك
as long as there are reinforcements.
يكفي أن تكون التعزيزات قادمة
The area outside the cave is heavily guarded by my father's men.
رجال والدي ينتشرون في كل مكان خارج هذا الكهف
You'd better not act rashly
وإلى حين وصول التعزيزات
before the reinforcements arrive.
من الأفضل ألا نتصرف بتهور
I'll remove all the candles outside.
سأزيل كل الشموع الموجودة في الخارج
This is the only thing I can do for you.
فهذه هي الطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكنني مساعدتكما بها
Hold on.
تمهّل
This is what your sister asked me to give
هذه أمانة
to you when she was alive.
أوصتني أختك بتسليمها إليك
If this plan fails tomorrow,
إن فشلت خطتنا غدًا
I will definitely end up dead.
فسأُقتل لا محالة
Please pass this letter on to my brother.
أرجو أن تسلّم هذه الرسالة إلى أخي الأصغر
If you are going to make a move,
إن قررتما التحرك
you'd better rescue all the people below.
فعليكما إنقاذ المحتجزين في الأسفل أيضًا
When will your reinforcements arrive?
متى ستصل تعزيزاتك؟
Qing Long and Yan Yue will send word.
سيبعث تشينغ لونغ ويان يوه إشارة عند وصولهم
Don't worry,
اطمئني
they will definitely ensure the safety
سنضمن أولًا سلامة الأميرة
of the Princess and Yuan Xiaoliu first.
ويوان شياو ليو
Then let's rest
إذًا دعنا نرتاح قليلًا الآن
to conserve our strength.
ونستجمع قوانا
♪ One glance from near stirs my heart ♪
خاطرة واحدة تغرق القلب في محنته ♪ ♪ ونظرة واحدة تبدّل كل شيء
♪ This fleeting moment ♪
♪ في هذه اللحظة ♪
♪ Tugs the threads woven by fate ♪
♪ تتشابك خيوط القدر ♪
♪ Bound tight evermore ♪
♪ لتربط بيننا إلى الأبد ♪
♪ Sharing all the years together ♪
♪ ونمضي معًا في رحلة العمر ♪
♪ Peace I find nowhere but by your side ♪
♪ فلا سكينة لي إلا بقربك ♪
♪ Bear witness with our souls ♪
♪ وما دامت الأرواح تتلاقى بصدق ♪
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
♪ فلن نهاب الفراق ولا تقلّبات الزمان ♪
Don't overthink it.
لا تبالغ في التفكير
I'm just afraid your injuries are too severe
إنما أخشى أن تكون إصابتك بالغة
for you to make it out of here alive.
وتموت هنا
♪ You know me and decided to live and die together ♪
♪ تعلم أنني إن عزمت، شاركتك المصير ♪
♪ Believe in my persistence that I won't run away ♪
♪ ثق بإصراري الذي لا يلين ♪
♪ You know I'm unyielding ♪
♪ تعلم أنني أواجه بعناد وشرف ♪
♪ Don't give up or dodge ♪
♪ لا أستسلم ولا أتوارى ♪
♪ Sincere hearts remain as of old ♪
♪ وقلبي صادق كما عهدتني دائمًا ♪
I...
أنا
♪ One glance from near stirs my heart ♪
خاطرة واحدة تغرق القلب في محنته ♪ ♪ ونظرة واحدة تبدّل كل شيء
I'm not treating you well because of the Phoenix Heart Token
لم أعاملكِ بلطف بسبب أمر تشيوه قو
♪ This fleeting moment ♪
♪ في هذه اللحظة ♪
that the Princess gave me.
الذي سلّمتني إياه الأميرة
Both Her Highness and I
فأنا والأميرة
♪ Tugs the threads woven by fate ♪
♪ تتشابك خيوط القدر ♪
wish for you to live freely and happily.
نأمل أن تعيشي بحرية وسعادة
♪ Bound tight evermore ♪
♪ لتربط بيننا إلى الأبد ♪
♪ Sharing all the years together ♪
♪ ونمضي معًا في رحلة العمر ♪
Jiayu.
جيا يوي
♪ Peace I find nowhere but by your side ♪
♪ فلا سكينة لي إلا بقربك ♪
I...
...أنا
♪ Bear witness with our souls ♪
♪ وما دامت الأرواح تتلاقى بصدق ♪
Xiao Wuyi.
شياو وو يي
Are you sure
هل أنت واثق
♪ Fear no partings or wax and wane ♪
♪ فلن نهاب الفراق ولا تقلّبات الزمان ♪
you can rescue all those people?
من أنك تستطيع إنقاذهم جميعًا؟
I can.
أستطيع
♪ You know me, seeing things through from start to finish ♪
♪ وتعلم أنني أُتمُّ ما بدأته حتى النهاية ♪
You're bragging.
!يا لك من متفاخر
I can pull it off if you trust me.
إذا وثقتِ بي، فيمكنني فعلها
♪ You see my move under rebellious cover ♪
♪ وترى ما خلف كبريائي من رقة ♪
♪ You know me, I'm willing to be with you till the end ♪
♪ وتعلم أنني سأبقى إلى جانبك حتى النهاية ♪
Okay.
حسنًا
♪ Burn the fire in my heart ♪
♪ حتى تخبو نار القلب ♪
I believe you.
أنا أثق بك
♪ Sincere hearts remain as of old ♪
♪ المدينة الحمراء، تماما كما كانت من قبل ♪
I know this risky path I walk may lead only to death.
أعلم أن مغامرتي هذه قد تكلّفني حياتي
However, the Cui family's evil deeds actually started because of me.
لكن جرائم عائلة تسوي كلها بدأت بسببي
If I hadn't tried to outdo you
فلولا أنني جادلت أبي بدافع العناد قديمًا
and reminded Father that, compared to adult men,
وأشرت إليه أن ممرات المنجم ضيقة
perhaps women might be better suited
وأن النساء، لكونهن أكثر رشاقة
to the narrow mine tunnels
أقدر على التسلل فيها من الرجال
and wouldn't be discovered by the authorities,
دون أن تكتشفهن السلطات
we wouldn't have committed so many murders now.
لما أُزهقت كل تلك الأرواح
Plenty of women were tricked into coming to Lingfeng Fort
لقد خُدعت نساء كثيرات واستُدرجن إلى حصن لينغفنغ
and lost their lives for a bit of grain and money.
ولقين حتفهن من أجل حفنة أرز أو بضع نقود
Thankfully, Princess Yunzhao discovered the secret of the mines.
ولحسن الحظ، اكتشفت الأميرة يونتشاو سر المنجم
I saved her
فأنقذتها
and helped her lure Young Lord Xiao here
واستدرجت إليها ولي العهد شياو
in order to atone for my sins.
تكفيرًا عن ذنبي
Shao'an, I know you want me to leave Lingfeng Fort
أخي، أعلم أنك أردت لي أن أغادر حصن لينغفنغ
and live a peaceful life.
وأعيش بقية عمري بسلام
But since the mistake has been made, I must pay with my life.
لكن الخطأ قد وقع، ويجب أن أدفع ثمنه بحياتي
If you continue to help the evildoer,
وإن واصلتَ إعانة الظالم على ظلمه
I will not be able to rest in peace.
فلن تهدأ روحي حتى بعد الموت
I hope my death can ignite your will to live.
أتمنى أن يشعل موتي إرادتك في الحياة
Only you know the way to save those women.
فأنت الوحيد الذي يعرف كيف ينقذ هؤلاء النساء
[Lingfeng Fort]
[حصن لينغفنغ]
Hey!
!أيها الحراس
Who the heck locked me up?
من الذي قيدني؟
Say something!
تكلموا
It's been so many days,
لقد مرّت أيام عديدة
and no one's ever come!
ولم أرَ أحدًا
Why not kill him, Master?
لماذا لا تقتله يا سيدي؟
What if...
...ماذا لو
Prince Qi's escort team
موكب زفاف أمير تشي
is already near Guazhou.
وصل بالفعل إلى خارج قواتشو
Princess Pingning
وهذه المرة
came in person this time.
قدِمت أميرة بينغنينغ بنفسها
They came right on time.
لقد جاءت في الوقت المناسب
How many days has it been since we last heard from Cui Xi?
لم ترد أي أخبار من تسوي شي منذ أيام
There are new updates every day.
تصل تقارير جديدة يوميًا
Everything is as usual at the Cui Mansion in Jiankang.
وكل شيء في قصر تسوي في جيانكانغ يسير كالمعتاد
I see.
علمت
By the way,
بالمناسبة
you must not mistreat him.
احرص على معاملته معاملة حسنة
Understood.
أمرك
Are you kidnapping me for my money or my looks?
هل تريدون مالي أم جسدي؟
Just tell me directly!
أعطوني إجابة واضحة
I'm fine with either!
كلاهما يروق لي
Greetings, Father.
أبي
Prince Qi has sent his younger sister,
لقد أرسل أمير تشي شقيقته
Princess Pingning,
أميرة بينغنينغ
to Lingfeng Fortress to escort the bride.
إلى حصن لينغفنغ لتأخذ العروس
From now on,
ومن اليوم فصاعدًا
she will be your older sister,
ستكون أختك الكبرى
Cui Lingyi.
تسوي لينغ يي
Father.
أبي
She is not my...
...إنها ليست
Turn your head around.
أدر رأسك
Bow.
انحنِ لها
S-Sister.
أختي... أختي الكبرى
Xie Jiayu
شيه جيا يوي
made the white silk flower for your sister, right?
هي من صنعت زهرة الحرير البيضاء هذه لأختك، أليس كذلك؟
Didn't you miss your sister so much?
أنت تفتقد أختك بشدة، أليس كذلك؟
Then stay here and behave yourself.
إذًا ابقَ مطيعًا هنا
Without my order,
ومن دون أمري
you shall not leave this place even by a single step.
لا تخطُ خطوة واحدة بعيدًا عن هذا المكان
[Lingfeng Fort]
[حصن لينغفنغ]
I spent over 20 years
لقد أمضيتُ أكثر من عشرين عامًا
cracking the secret in the Phoenix Heart Token
حتى كشفت سر أمر تشيوه قو
and discovering the iron mine under this mountain.
واكتشفت منجم الحديد الكامن تحت هذا الجبل
But it's a pity that
لكن، للأسف
an accident happened halfway through the excavation.
ما إن بلغنا منتصف الحفر حتى وقعت الكارثة
The groundwater has been contaminated,
حيث تلوثت المياه الجوفية
and anyone who touches it will get hit by a strange disease.
وكل من لامسها أصيب بذلك الداء الغريب
Last night, Xiao Wuyi
البارحة، قتل شياو وو يي
killed a maniac with the strange disease.
مجنونًا أصابه ذلك المرض
Your Highness, if you still refuse to hand over the Phoenix Heart Token,
وإن أصرت الأميرة على عدم تسليم أمر تشيوه قو
then the next one to get infected
فإن الشخص التالي الذي سيصاب بالمرض
will be Xie Jiayu.
ستكون شيه جيا يوي
If she gets infected,
وإذا أصيبت بالمرض
I wonder if Young Lord Xiao
أتساءل إن كان ولي العهد شياو
would give her a quick death.
سيكون على استعداد لمنحها موتًا سريعًا
Take this hairpin
خذ دبوس الشعر هذا
and go to the Nandu Wharf we agreed on back then.
واذهب إلى مرسى ناندو الذي اتفقنا عليه قديمًا
Seeing this hairpin,
يكفي أن يكون الدبوس معك
someone will contact you.
وسيتواصل معك أحدهم لا محالة
I can't believe you hid the Phoenix Heart Token
لقد أخفيتِ أمر تشيوه قو
at the old Nandu Wharf.
في مرسى ناندو في تلك السنة
Guards,
يا حراس
seal off all the mines at the foot of the mountain
اطمروا جميع الأنفاق في المنجم أسفل الجبل
and let no one get out of there.
ولا تسمحوا لأحد بمغادرة المنجم ولو خطوة
-Understood.
أمرك
Take Her Highness away
خذوا الأميرة
and lock her up.
وشددوا الحراسة عليها
Cui Jun!
تسوي جيون
You broke your word!
لقد نكثتَ بوعدك
It's not the first time.
هذه ليست المرة الأولى
Aren't you afraid that everything I told you is fake?
ألا تخشى أن يكون كل ما قلته لك كذبًا؟
The worst case is that I'll kill both you
في أسوأ الأحوال، سأرسلك أنتِ وابنتكِ
and your daughter.
إلى القبر معًا
Take her away.
خذوها
Stop wandering. You're making me dizzy.
كُفي عن الدوران، لقد أصابني الدوار
Do you think Qing Long and Yan Yue have been caught?
هل تعتقد أن تشينغ لونغ ويان يوه قد وقعا في الأسر؟
Where are your reinforcements?
وأين تعزيزاتك؟
Why hasn't there been any response?
لماذا لا أثر لها؟
Rest assured.
اطمئني
Before I entered Lingfeng Fort,
قبل أن أدخل حصن لينغفنغ
the reinforcements were already on their way.
كانت التعزيزات في طريقها بالفعل
I didn't come here because of
ولم أُستدرج إلى هنا
the Princess's family letter.
بسبب رسالة الأميرة
Before I came here,
فقبل مجيئي
some people in the Beifu Army
أُصيب بعض جنود جيش الشمال
contracted the same strange disease as those in the mines.
بالداء نفسه الذي أصاب من كانوا في المنجم
They ate the rations issued by the imperial court
لقد تناولوا مؤنًا عسكرية أرسلها البلاط
that had been soaked in contaminated water.
كانت قد نُقعت في مياه ملوثة
And those rations came from Guazhou.
وتلك المؤن العسكرية مصدرها قواتشو
Someone must have learned the secret about Guazhou
لا بد أن أحدهم اكتشف ما يجري في قواتشو
and dragged the Beifu soldiers into this
فتعمد توريط جيش الشمال في الأمر
just in order to lure me here.
ليستدرجني إلى هنا
It can not only deal a blow to the Beifu Reform
فبهذا يمكنه أن يضر بإصلاح الحامية الشمالية
but also destroy the Cui family.
ويدفع بعائلة تسوي إلى الهلاك بحجرٍ واحد
I guess the person behind this
وأرجح أن من يقف وراء ذلك
is the Grand Tutor.
هو المعلم الأكبر
My father?
أبي؟
The Grand Tutor and the Cui family
يبدو أن بين المعلم الأكبر وعائلة تسوي
probably have a blood feud.
ثأرًا لا يهدأ حتى بإبادة العائلة
Judging from the time,
وبحسب الوقت
Li Mao must have
فلا بد أن لي ماو قد بدأ الآن
raided the Cui Mansion in Jiankang by now.
بالهجوم على قصر تسوي في جيانكانغ
The people he dispatched from Jiankang
أما الرجال الذين أرسلهم من جيانكانغ
should arrive in a few days.
فمن المفترض أن يصلوا قريبًا
You... Why didn't you tell me earlier?
أنت... لماذا لم تخبرني بهذا من قبل؟
You guys, go there.
أنتم، اذهبوا إلى هناك
-Understood!
أمرك
And you.
وأنت
They are locked up in the cell ahead.
إنهم محتجزون في الزنزانة الأمامية
Understood.
أمرك
What is he doing here?
ما الذي جاء به إلى هنا؟
Sealing off the mines.
لردم المنجم
Don't be afraid.
لا تخافي
According to my master's order,
لقد أوصى السيد
you two are distinguished guests,
بأن تُعاملا كضيفين كريمين
and the path to the afterlife is a painful one.
لكن طريق العالم الآخر شاق وطويل
If you want to die a quick death,
لذا إن أردتما موتًا سريعًا
you can take this poison.
فتناولا هذا الدواء
It seems that Cui Jun
يبدو أن تسوي جيون
really wants me dead.
عازم حقًا على قتلي
Master!
معلمي
Where have you been the past few days?
أين كنت طوال اليومين الماضيين؟
I don't even want to bring it up. You wouldn't believe me.
لا تسألي، لن تصدقيني إذا أخبرتكِ
The past few days,
طوال الأيام القليلة الماضية
I've been eating well for all 3 meals every day.
كنت أتناول أطيب الطعام وأشرب أفخر الشراب
Except for that mute who delivered the food,
وباستثناء ذلك الأبكم الذي كان يجلب الطعام
I didn't see anyone else.
لم أرَ أحدًا على الإطلاق
Wait,
لا
w-why? There's no way!
ولكن... لماذا نحن هكذا؟
Look...
...انظر... أنت
Hurry.
أسرع، أسرع، أسرع
Sorry.
عذرًا
Where are Qing Long and Yan Yue?
أين تشينغ لونغ ويان يوه؟
You were not led here by them?
ألم يكونا هما من استدرجاك إلى هنا؟
No.
لا
It was Cui Shao'an.
لقد كان تسوي شاو آن
The mines in the back mountain.
منجم الجبل الخلفي
The Cui family is grateful for His Majesty's grace.
إن عائلة تسوي ليُقدّرون عظيم فضل جلالته
I am willing to be diligent and self-disciplined,
لذا أتعهد أنا المنتمي لعائلة تسوي بأن أتحلى بالاجتهاد وضبط النفس
strictly follow the imperial edict,
وأن أمتثل بكل تواضع للمرسوم الإمبراطوري
form a marriage alliance with Prince Qi,
القاضي بتكوين رابطة زواج مع أمير تشي
and devote my absolute loyalty and effort to the state.
وأن أخدم الدولة بكل إخلاص وتفانٍ
I will not fail His Majesty's grace.
وألا أخيب النعمة السماوية
I, Cui Lingyi, am willing to serve Prince Qi
وأنا، خادمتكِ لينغ يي من عائلة تسوي أتعهد بخدمة سمو الأمير
and be of one mind and principle with His Highness
وأن أكون معه قلبًا وقالبًا
to protect our family and state,
وبأن أصون العائلة والوطن
with fidelity for the rest of my life.
وبأن أحيا حياة تليق بهذا الاتحاد
You may rise.
انهضي
Wait!
!تمهلوا
You rebellious child!
!أيها الابن العاق
Today is your sister's big day of being escorted as the bride.
اليوم هو يوم زفاف شقيقتك الكبرى
What are you going to do?
فما الذي تنوي فعله؟
Guards! Take my unfilial son out!
أيها الحراس! أخرجوا هذا الابن العاق من هنا
I, Cui Shao'an, pay my respects
أنا المذنب تسوي شاو آن
to you, Princess Pingning.
أؤدي التحية لأميرة بينغنينغ
You killed...
لقد قتلتها
The one I killed is not my real sister.
من قتلتها ليست أختي الحقيقية
You brat!
!أيها الابن العاق
Cui Shao'an,
تسوي شاو آن
what did you just say?
ماذا قلت للتو؟
My sister, Cui Lingyi,
إن أختي، تسوي لينغ يي
was killed by my father long ago,
قتلها أبي بيديه منذ زمن
with her body destroyed overnight.
ثم دمر جثمانها سرًّا في الليلة نفسها لإخفاء معالم الجريمة
If you don't believe me,
إذا لم تصدقيني يا سمو الأميرة
Your Highness, here is my sister's handwritten letter
فهذه رسالة كتبتها أختي بخط يدها
as well as the evidence of the crimes that my Cui family
ومعها الأدلة التي خاطرت أختي بحياتها لتحافظ عليها
has committed over the past 20 years,
وهي إثباتات على جرائم عائلة تسوي
which my sister left behind at the price of her life!
التي ارتكبتها طوال العشرين عامًا الماضية
Please take a look, Your Highness!
أرجو من سموكِ الاطلاع عليها
What are these bloody contracts?
ما هذه العقود الملطخة بالدماء؟
Cui Jun, you've not only run illegal private mines
تسوي جيون، أنت لم تكتفِ بتشغيل منجم غير مشروع
but also harmed young girls and children
بل مارست الوحشية ضد الفتيات والأطفال
and made them mine for you,
وأجبرتهم على العمل في المنجم لصالحك
causing countless unjust deaths.
وأزهقت أرواحًا لا تُحصى
Do you even care about the imperial court and the people?
فأين مكانة البلاط والرعية في حساباتك؟
How can you claim to stand with Prince Qi
وبأي وجه تزعم أنك ستعاون أمير تشي
in protecting the state
في حماية البلاد
and carrying out a great cause?
وحمل المسؤولية الكبرى؟
Guards!
!أيها الحراس
Your Highness, you came to Lingfeng Fort with the armed Imperial Guards
سمو الأميرة، لقد جئتِ بذريعة استقبال العروس
under the guise of escorting the bride.
لكنكِ أخفيتِ سيوف الحرس الإمبراطوري
What are you up to?
فما هي نيتكِ من المجيء إلى حصن لينغفنغ؟
Cui Jun, are you trying to rebel?
تسوي جيون، هل تحاول التمرد؟
Listen up, guys.
استمعوا إليّ جميعًا
Whoever kills Li Lejun will be
من يقتل لي له جيون
rewarded with 1,000 households' tax revenues and 10,000 taels of gold!
سيُمنح إقطاعية تضم ألف أسرة ومكافأة قدرها عشرة آلاف ليانغ من الذهب
Brother!
أخي
Sister!
أختي
Kill them, and you'll be
اقتلوهم
rewarded based on merits!
وستنالون المكافآت كلٌّ بحسب أدائه
Who dares to make a move?
أريد أن أرى من منكم يجرؤ على ذلك
We're standing here today.
سنقف هنا اليوم
You can make your move
يمكنكم أن تهاجمونا
and kill all of us!
وأن تقتلونا جميعًا
But look at these faces.
لكن انظروا جيدًا إلى هذه الوجوه
Are they any different
هل يختلفن عن أمهاتكم وأخواتكم وبناتكم
from your own families?
في أي شيء؟
If you raise your blades to kill us today,
إن رفعتم السيوف عليهن اليوم
someone will use the same blades
فسيأتي يوم يوجه فيه السيف نفسه
to murder your families tomorrow!
إلى رقاب أحبائكم
Bring her here!
أحضروها إلى هنا
Mother!
أمي
Xie Jiayu, Xiao Wuyi,
شيه جيا يوي، شياو وو يي
if you take one more step forward,
إن تقدمتما خطوة أخرى
I'll have Yunzhao
فسأجعل يونتشاو
die in front of you right away.
تموت أمام أعينكما في الحال
Cui Jun,
تسوي جيون
don't you dare.
هل تجرؤ على ذلك؟
Xiao Wuyi, you...
...شياو وو يي، أنت
This is the Beifu Army's war drum.
هذا صوت طبول الحرب لجيش الشمال
Xiao Wuyi,
شياو وو يي
when did you set this up?
متى أعددت لهذه الخطة؟
Since the moment Princess Yunzhao told you
منذ اللحظة التي أخبرتك فيها الأميرة
the Phoenix Heart Token's whereabouts.
بمكان أمر تشيوه قو
Qing Long, Yan Yue!
تشينغ لونغ، يان يوه
This is the totem of Northern Qin's Eagle King.
هذا هو شعار أمير النسر من تشين الشمالية
Yes, they are all the Eagle King's henchmen
صحيح، إنهم جميعًا من تشين الشمالية
from Northern Qin.
وأتباع أمير النسر
Cui Jun,
تسوي جيون
the Eagle King of Northern Qin is the client of your private mines.
أمير النسر من تشين الشمالية هو المشتري لمنجمك السري
You have been colluding with Northern Qin all along.
لقد تواطأت مع تشين الشمالية طوال هذا الوقت
How audacious you are.
!يا لجرأتك
Cui Jun,
تسوي جيون
over 20 years ago,
قبل أكثر من عشرين عامًا
when Northern Qin attacked the Capital,
حين قامت تشين الشمالية بغزو شانغجينغ
you were accusing
كنت أنت أول من وشى
the An and Lu families for the first time.
بعشيرتي آن ولو الأرستقراطيتين الكبيرتين
Could it be that you had already colluded with Northern Qin back then,
فهل يُعقل أنك متواطئ مع تشين الشمالية منذ ذلك الحين؟
causing the horrible bloodshed in the Capital?
ولهذا غرقت شانغجينغ في بحر من الدماء؟
What horrible bloodshed?
أي بحر دماء؟
I only know that the Ans and Lus conspired with the enemy and committed treason.
كل ما أعرفه هو أن عشيرتي آن ولو خانتا البلاد
I only know that Emperor Wenxi was licentious and brutal,
وأن إمبراطور ونشي كان طاغيةً فاسدًا
bringing destruction to the state and families.
حتى أضاع البلاد وأهلك الرعية
How dare you!
!وقاحة
How dare you slander the late Emperor?
كيف تجرؤ على الافتراء على الإمبراطور الراحل؟
Don't forget that
لا تنسَ
you are Empress Wenxi's brother
أنك شقيق إمبراطورة ونشي
and the Phoenix Heart Token holder,
وحامل أمر تشيوه قو
bearing the responsibility of moving Ye south
وقد أُلقي على عاتقكما عبء هجرة يه الكبرى جنوبًا
and assisting Crown Prince Wenxi...
ومساندة ولي عهد ونشي
Crown Prince Wenxi died long ago!
لقد مات ولي عهد ونشي منذ زمن
He is not dead!
إنه لم يمت
Crown Prince Wenxi is not dead?
!ولي عهد ونشي لم يمت
Tell me.
أخبريني
Who is Crown Prince Wenxi?
من هو ولي عهد ونشي؟
Where is he hiding?
وأين يختبئ؟
Mother!
أمي
Are you okay?
هل أنتِ بخير؟
I'm fine.
أنا بخير